<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mans extremity, Gods opportunity, or, A display of Gods sovereign grace in saving a people whose recovery as to men and means is next to desperate as it was delivered in a sermon preached before the Honourable Lieutenant governour ... of the province of the Massachusetts Bay in New England on May 29, 1695 which was the day for election of counsellors for that province / by the reverend Mr. Samuel Torrey.</title>
            <author>Torrey, Samuel, 1632-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1695</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62961</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1917</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R30168</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11254760</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11254760</idno>
            <idno type="VID">47161</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62961)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 47161)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1451:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mans extremity, Gods opportunity, or, A display of Gods sovereign grace in saving a people whose recovery as to men and means is next to desperate as it was delivered in a sermon preached before the Honourable Lieutenant governour ... of the province of the Massachusetts Bay in New England on May 29, 1695 which was the day for election of counsellors for that province / by the reverend Mr. Samuel Torrey.</title>
                  <author>Torrey, Samuel, 1632-1707.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Bartholomew Green for Michael Perry ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1695.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Election sermons --  Massachusetts.</term>
               <term>Sermons, American --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:47161:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:47161:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>MANS Extremity, GODS OPPORTUNITY. OR, A Diſplay of GODS Sovereign Grace, in Saving a PEOPLE whoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery, as to Men and Means is next to deſperate: As it was delivered in A SERMON Preached before the Honourable Lieutenant Governour, &amp; Counſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lors, and the Aſſembly of Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentatives of the Province of the <hi>Maſſachuſetts Bay</hi> in <hi>New England.</hi> On <hi>MAY</hi> 29. 1695. Which was the Day for ELECTION of Counſellors for that Province. By the Reverend Mr. <hi>SAM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EL TORREY,</hi> Paſtor of the Church in <hi>Weymouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iſa. 57.18.</hi>
               </bibl> I have ſeen his ways, &amp; will heal him.</q>
            <p>BOSTON, Printed by <hi>Bartholomew Green,</hi> for <hi>Michael Perry,</hi> under the Weſt end of the. Town-houſe. 1695.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:47161:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Order of Authority.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:47161:2"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HOW Seaſonable the following Diſcourſe was and how well accommodated to the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion for which it was Levelled, and Audience before whom it was Delivered, may poſſibly be queſtioned by ſuch as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are poſseſsed with an overweening O pinion of a Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative Commendation given us, that we are not ſo bad, or ſo far gone as many other People who make a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion; or are little concerned in obſerving, either Men or Providences, and comparing them with Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Rules: But he that ſhall ſeriouſly ponder how far we are declined from what we ſometimes were; how many things are <hi>Dead</hi> among us, and how thoſe <hi>that Remain are ready to dy;</hi> how much God hath done for us more than for many others, and how we have <hi>Requited</hi> him; how long he hath been deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with us in a way of Judgments, and what means have been uſed to Reclaim us; all which notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, neither are we returned to God, nor is his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger turned away from us; cannot but Subſcribe to it, and ſay, it was <hi>a Word upon it's Wheels.</hi> And truly, when we are caſt in <hi>Common Law,</hi> what have we to hope in but <hi>Prerogative Mercy?</hi> When Good Men in all Orders find all attempts to recover a Backſlidden People awfully to be fruſtrated, needs muſt they ſink in diſpondency, and loſe their Faith and Hope, did they not encourage them by this conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that as God can, ſo he frequently doth, take ſuch an Opportunity to make himſelf known; and ſo have the whole Glory of ſuch a Peoples Salvation aſcribed to him.
<pb facs="tcp:47161:3"/>The Author of this Sermon, is one whoſe <hi>Works Praiſe him in the Gates,</hi> and cannot be added to by any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of mine. He hath lived to ſee many changes in this Land; and being awfully ſenſible of the decays of Practical Holineſs, and the ſolemn Tokens of Divine diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure at a People who were ſometimes highly favoured by their God; hath on all Occaſions been ready to thruſt into the <hi>Gap,</hi> and endeavour the preventing of Ruin, by promoting a thorow <hi>Reformation:</hi> but finding how little Succeſs ſuch Eſsays have had, hath thereupon, with <hi>Eli, Sat trembling for the Ark of the God of Iſrael:</hi> &amp; <hi>had fainted, but that he believed to ſee the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of God.</hi> He hath here told us, where he found relief against his ſinking and overwhelming thoughts, even in him who works for his <hi>Great Name,</hi> when it hath been <hi>Profaned</hi> by a People of his <hi>Covenant:</hi> and hath recommended it for an excellent help to encourage the Faith, and animate the Prayers of the truly Godly unto perſeverance in waiting to <hi>See Gods Salvations;</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuring us that neither our Sins, nor our preſent Impeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, can obſtruct Gods Grace, or prevent his appearing for our help, in <hi>Subduing our Iniquities,</hi> and reſtoring us to his favour: that when times are never ſo black, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond cauſes afford little or no relief, and <hi>there is none ſhut up or left,</hi> yet <hi>Caelo reſtat iter,</hi> and there is <hi>THEOS APO MECHANES.</hi> That the Publication of this Sermon, may anſwer the deſires of theſe who earneſtly ſought for it, and be made profitable, as to ſhow us more of our own State, ſo to put us upon greater induſtry in all preſent neceſsary duties; and (becauſe <hi>there is yet hope in Iſrael,</hi>) to ſet upon the work ſo often ſolemnly preſsed upon us, &amp; hitherto ſo little purſued, ſhall be the Prayer of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>One that waits for the Conſolation of Iſrael, S. WILLARD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:47161:3"/>
            <head>MANS EXTREMITY, <hi>GODS OPPORT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NITY.</hi>
            </head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Hoſea I. 7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>But I will have mercy upon the Houſe of Judah; and will Save them by the Lord their God.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WE find in the Context, that the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> (that is) the ten Tribes having by their Spiritual Whoredoms, given not only Conception, but, Birth both unto <hi>Loru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h</hi> and <hi>Loammi:</hi> God in his Holy Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie and Righteous Judgment, had reſolved to caſt them off for their Apoſtacy, unto Idolatry, as a Reprobate People? Wherefore,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:47161:4"/>he raiſed up and ſent this Prophet, to give them the ſad and certain intelligence, of that his moſt dreadful Reſolve againſt them; the Prophet having received his doleful Meſſage, in a grievous Viſion; he delivers it in a moſt direful Threatning, at once denouncing the utmoſt Extremity, of all kind of Calamity and Miſery, in their being given up totally, both unto Sin and Judgment; this we have in the latter part of the <hi>ſixth verſe. I will no more have mercy upon the Houſe of Iſrael; but I will utterly take them away!</hi> And further, to Accumulate, and Exaggerate, this heavy Threathing in the burthen of it, upon the Houſe of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> God doth at the ſame time, and in the very next words, propoſe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim, a very gracious and glorious Promiſe, of Mercy and Salvation, to the Houſe of <hi>Judah, verſe</hi> 7. <hi>But I will have mercy upon the Houſe of Judah, and will ſave them by the Lord their God. Judah</hi> (was at this time) a very <hi>Sinful, Backſliding People;</hi> ſinking into a depth of groſs Apoſtacy to Idolatry alſo; which God upbraids them with, judging and condemning them, as more <hi>vile</hi> and <hi>inexcuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> than <hi>Iſrael, Jer.</hi> 3.11. Yet God, in his Sovereign Grace, makes a ſure Promiſe of Mercy and Salvation, to <hi>Judah! Buts I will have mercy upon the Houſe of Judah;</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gageth himſelf to perform it, by Saving of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:47161:4"/>them, in a more immediate and extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry way of working by himſelf; <hi>and will ſave them by the Lord their God;</hi> intimating thereby, that <hi>Judah</hi> alſo was paſt hope of Salvation in any ordinary way: Whence we have this</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>DOCTRINE. <hi>That at ſome times, and in ſome caſes, God doth in Sovereign Mercy, Save his Churches and People, both from Sin and Judgment, in a more immediate and extraordinary way of working by himſelf.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>I will have mercy upon the Houſe of Judah, and will ſave them by the Lord their God:</hi> This great comprehenſive Promiſe contains the Summe of all Promiſes of <hi>Temporal</hi> Salvation to the Church, both from Sin and Judgment, which God hath made, or doth accompliſh, in this world; and therefore it hath been, and doth remain the foundation of Faith, Hope, Confidence &amp; Comfort, to the Church in all Ages, in their greateſt depths, when they have been moſt ready to periſh in their Apoſtacy, Calamity and Miſery. The <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes</hi> of God, the <hi>Prayers</hi> of the Church, and <hi>all the most Notable Instances</hi> of ſuch glorious Salvations, which we find recorded in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:47161:5"/>Word of God, do all concur, to prove; <hi>That God at ſome times, and in ſome caſes, doth in Sovereign Grace, ſave his Churches, both from Sin and Judgment in a more Immediate and Extraordinary Way of working by himſelf:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Doctrine opens it ſelf unto us, with a fulneſs of Scripture Evidence in the ſeveral parts of it;</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That all Salvations to the Children of men are from God;</hi> He who is <hi>God alone,</hi> muſt needs be the only Saviour; therefore he is emphatically ſtyled, <hi>the Saviour;</hi> Iſa. 45.15. <hi>O God of Iſrael the Saviour;</hi> and verſe 21. <hi>There is no God elſe beſides me, a juſt God and a Saviour;</hi> Iſa. 43.11. <hi>I even I am the Lord, and beſides me there is no Saviour;</hi> therefore he is ſtyled the God of Salvation, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.20. <hi>He that is our God is the God of Salvation;</hi> hence <hi>Salvation belongs only to the Lord, Pſal.</hi> 3.8. all who know and believe him to be God, muſt needs acknowledge him to be the only Author of all, both Temporal, Spiritual and Eternal Salvations, to all the Children of men, who partake of any Salvations, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 45.22. <hi>Look unto me and be ye Saved, all the Ends of the Earth, for I am God, and there is none elſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2 <hi>That God works divers kinds and degrees of Salvation:</hi> there are divers wayes of Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, wherein God works as a Saviour; there are external, common, general Salvations,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:47161:5"/>which God works in his common Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence; theſe God works in divers waves and degrees for all the Children of men. By theſe Salvations it is that he moderates all the Evils of the Curſe, ſo far as to give man a Being and Subſiſtence in this world, more or leſs comfortable, as ſeemeth good to him; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107. <hi>per tot.</hi> We have an Induction of ſuch kind of Salvations, with a reiterated Exhortation, <hi>To Praiſe the Lord for his Goodneſs and for his wonderful Works to the Children of men:</hi> Again, God works ſuch Salvation <hi>in common Providence alſo,</hi> but in <hi>ſpecial Mercy</hi> to his Churches and People, Deut. 33.29. <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py art thou O Iſrael, who is like to thee, a People Saved by the Lord.</hi> There are alſo <hi>Special Salvations</hi> which God worketh for his Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and People, in the way of his <hi>Spiritual Providence,</hi> in <hi>Saving Mercy;</hi> which are the only Saving Salvations, and which hold a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary Connection with <hi>Eternal Salvation;</hi> this is the moſt glorious Salvation which God works for his People in this World, when he Saves his People from their Sins, and from all Spiritual Evils and Enemies, and to this all Promiſes of Salvation to the Church in this World, do ultimately referr. This is, and will be the Conſummation of all Temporal Salvations to the Church in this World, as it will appear gloriouſly in the laſt and full Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:47161:6"/>compliſhment of this Promiſe in our Text, when that Acclamation ſhall be heard, Rev. 12.10. <hi>Now is come Salvation and Strength, the Kingdom of our God, and the Power of his Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>That God works all, both Temporal and Spiritual Salvations for his Churches and People,</hi> either <hi>more Mediately or more Immediately:</hi> he works common Salvation in a way of medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate, ordinary Providence; and ſo all Gods Propitious, Proſperous Providences may be ſaid to be Salvations? God works ſpecial, extraordinary Salvations for his People in a <hi>more Immediate, Extraordinary way of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence;</hi> although it may not be altogether <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately,</hi> yet <hi>more immediately;</hi> there may be a more Immediate Influence of Divine Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Power, which may make the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion wrought, <hi>Wonderful,</hi> if not <hi>Miraculous;</hi> ſuch as God wrought for his Church of Old, in <hi>Egypt,</hi> in the Wilderneſs, in the times of the Judges, and of ſome of the Kings, and afterwards. In this way of working it is that God is ſaid to Save his People <hi>by his own Right Hand, and by his own Arm,</hi> Pſal. 44.3. Pſal. 77.15, and to Save them <hi>with an High Hand, and Out ſtretched Arm,</hi> Exod. 6.6. and 14.8. When the Lord <hi>doth make bare his Arm, then all the Ends of the Earth may ſee his Salvation:</hi> Iſa. 52.10. Moſt immediately God works,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:47161:6"/>in working of Spiritual Salvations: Now God may be ſaid to work more immediately.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>When he works as a Creator; when it is Creating Work,</hi> (and in ſome reſpects) the moſt Glorious Creating Work, or Work of Greation, for God to Create to himſelf a People, a Church, Pſal. 102.18. <hi>The People that ſhall be Created, ſhall Praiſe the Lord,</hi> ſo Iſa. 41.20. Iſa. 43.1. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord that Created thee, O Jacob,</hi> &amp;c. ver. 7. <hi>For I have Created him for my Glory;</hi> and ver. 15. <hi>I am the Lord, the Creator of Iſrael, your King.</hi> Sure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly God will work more gloriouſly by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, in Creating the <hi>New Heavens and the New Earth,</hi> Iſa. 65.17, 18. <hi>For behold I Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate New Heavens and a new Earth, be you glad and rejoice for ever in that which I Create; for behold, I Create Jeruſalem, a rejoycing, and her People a joy:</hi> Iſa. 45.8. <hi>Drop down ye Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens from above, and let the Skies pour down Righteouſneſs; let the Earth open, and let them bring forth Salvation: I the Lord have Created it.</hi> Obſerve, God <hi>Createth</hi> this moſt Glorious Spiritual Salvation for his Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>God works more immediately by himſelf in Saving of his People, when he works by a more full and glorious exerciſe of the Power of Chriſt Mediator.</hi> God works all Salvations by his Son; he is therefore eminently ſtyled, the <hi>Saviour;</hi> he hath wrought <hi>Spiritual and Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:47161:7"/>Redemption and Salvation;</hi> and <hi>he applies it to all his Elect: He is Exalted by Gods own Right-Hand, to be a Prince and a Saviour,</hi> Acts 5.31. <hi>There is Salvation in none other, nor any other Name given under Heaven amongſt men, whereby we can be Saved:</hi> Acts 4.12. he is therefore called <hi>Jeſus, Becauſe he came to Save his People from their Sins, Mat.</hi> 1.21. All Temporal Salvations wrought for the Church of Old, are attributed unto him; Iſa. 63.10. <hi>In all their Afflictions he was Afflicted, and the Angel of his Preſence ſaved them;</hi> God ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared and wrought by him, in Saving his People out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> Exod. 3.2. in the Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.20. and in bringing of them into <hi>Canaan,</hi> Joſh. 5.13, 14. and in bringing the Church out of <hi>Babilon,</hi> Zech. 1.12. thus God alwayes Saved his People by the <hi>Angel of his Preſence;</hi> and therefore all Salvations which God works for his People in all Ages of the World, until the Church Militant become Triumphant, are aſcribed to him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.10. <hi>Salvation to our God, and the Lamb;</hi> that is to God working more imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately by Chriſt <hi>Mediator.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3 <hi>God works more immediately to Save his People by himſelf; that is by his Spirit,</hi> Zech. 4.6. <hi>not by might nor by power, but by my Spirit, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts;</hi> that is more immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately <hi>by myſelf.</hi> This is none other than the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:47161:7"/>
                  <hi>ſame Promiſe</hi> with this in our Text, renewed <hi>just then,</hi> at the firſt <hi>period</hi> of the Signal Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of it; though it may have a more <hi>full and notable</hi> Accompliſhment, not only unto them, but to the whole Church of God in the World, at the <hi>time appointed;</hi> and truly, this great Promiſe of the Spirit, (ſo often renewed in the Scripture,) it hath been and ever will be in ſucceſſive Accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the Church; it is that whereby the Church hath lived, and been upheld in all Ages, as the ſoundation of their Faith, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence and Perſeverance.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>God works more immediately by his Word when he make it mighty and powerful, to all the ſaving Effects and Ends of it;</hi> eſpecially in the <hi>Converſion &amp; Reformation</hi> of his People; he works all ſaving work, all Spiritual Salvation for his Church by the means of the Miniſtry of his word; <hi>(that is)</hi> he works more <hi>imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately by this means,</hi> it being the higheſt means of the working of Divine Wiſdom and Power, eſpecially upon the Souls of men: the Church in their return out of Babylon, could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover themſelves, nor be recovered by any through Reformation unto Salvation until God wrought <hi>more immediately</hi> by the Miniſtry of his Word, in the <hi>Propheſying of Haggai and Zechary,</hi> Ezra. 6.14. as we read more at large Hag. 1.12, 13, 14. <hi>Then</hi> Zerubbabel <hi>the Son
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:47161:8"/>of</hi> Shealtiel <hi>and Joſhua the High Prieſt, with all the remnant of the people, did obey the voice of the Lord, and the words of Haggai the Prophet: and they did fear the Lord: then ſpake Haggai the Lords Meſſenger in the Lords Meſſage to the People, ſaying, I am with you ſaith the Lord;</hi> Obſerve, when the Word works, then God is with a people to Save them; therefore it follows, and the <hi>Lord ſtirred up the Spirit of</hi> Zernbbabel; Nothing could be done until God himſelf, wrought by himſelf in the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of his Word,</hi> and then all Saving Work went on powerfully and proſperouſly. Thus we may underſtand how God <hi>Saves his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by the Lord their God,</hi> which was the main thing to be opened and proved; But,</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>There are certain times, and extraordinary caſes, wherein God thus Saves his People by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> (that is) in general, when their Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in it ſelf, and as to them, is altogether <hi>hopeleſs</hi> and <hi>helpleſs;</hi> either reſpecting their Sins, growing more and more general, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful, incorrigible, poenal, judicial, paſt any ordinary hope of Reformation; their Defect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion and Apoſtacy in the Life and Power of Religion ſo deep, that there is no ordinary hope of recovery. All both Spiritual and Political Wounds &amp; Sickneſſes; ſo immedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; incurable that they are paſt ordinary hope of healing; ſo when a people are in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:47161:8"/>inevitable danger of periſhing in their own ſins, under Gods Judgments, both Temporal and Spiritual Judgments; unleſs God, in So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Mercy, appear and work Salvation for them by himſelf: When all things are <hi>paſt man, paſt means;</hi> when the Wiſdom, the Power, the Heart, the Spirit, the Prayers, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leavours and Labours of man fail, then it is time for the Church to cry out, as Pſal. 119.126. <hi>It is time for thee, Lord, to work:</hi> More particularly;</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>When a People are fallen into ſuch a depth of Spiritual Heart Apoſtacy, as that they are thereby become, not only ſecure, but utterly ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, ſottiſh, ſtupid, ſupine, and ſo altogether igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, careleſs, regardleſs of the greateſt Concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of their own Good and Welfare, and of their own Salvation, either from Sin or Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> as being ſenſeleſs of both, not minding. nor caring which way things go, nor what doth become of themſelves, or of the main intereſt of God, of Chriſt, or of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; ready to ſpeak as they, Ezek. 33.10. <hi>If our Tranſgreſſions and Iniquities be upon us, and we pine away in them, how then can we Live,</hi> as if they ſhould have ſaid, there is no hope, we ſhall periſh in our ſins, and thus they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, careleſly and deſperately; and as they, Iſa. 3.6. <hi>In that day ſhall he ſwear, ſaying, I will not be a Healer, make me not a Ruler of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:47161:9"/>People;</hi> It follows, verſe 8. <hi>For Jeruſalem is ruined, and Judah is fallen:</hi> Thus they gave up themſelves as deſperate.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>When thoſe who are ſincerely concerned for the Welfare and Salvation of the People and Churches, are altogether diſpirited, and ſuccumb under ſinking diſcouragements;</hi> Hearts fainting, Spirits failing, have no heart left in them, to make any further eſſay, or to do any thing, but to ſit down, Mourn, Weep and Lament, as the Prophet, Jer. 8.18. <hi>When I would com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort my ſelf againſt ſorrow, my heart is faint in me; the Har weſt is paſt, the Summer is ended, and we are not healed; for the hurt of the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te of my People, I am hurt, I am black, Aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment hath taken hold upon me: Is there no Balm in</hi> Gilead? <hi>Is there no Phyſician there?</hi> ſo Jer. 9.1. <hi>O that mine head were waters, and mine eyes a fountain of Tears, that I might weep day and night,</hi> &amp;c. ſo Mic. 7.1. <hi>Wo is me!</hi> When it is thus, it is time to cry, <hi>Help Lord!</hi> Pſal. 12.15.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>When God ſeems to have wrought, and done for a people, all that can ordinarily be done, by the improvement of means, to Save them from all deſtroying Evils,</hi> eſpecially from their Sins; and to reclaim and reduce them to himſelf; and to ſecure and advance both their Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and Spiritual Welfare. When God ſpeaks after the manner of men, as it were
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:47161:9"/>Complaining, Iſa. 5.4. <hi>What could have been done more to my Vineyard, that I have not done in it;</hi> ſo <hi>Jer.</hi> 9.7. <hi>I will melt them and try them, for what ſhall I do for the daughter of my People:</hi> Hoſ. 6.4. <hi>O Ephraim what ſhall I do unto thee? O Judah what ſhall I do unto thee?</hi> God ſpeaketh here as men do when they know not what to do more.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>When hereupon God doth ceaſe to work in an ordinary way by ordinary means, and leaves a people to themſelves;</hi> withdraws his Spirit, his Preſence, his Power, his Counſel, his Conduct, his Protection and Benediction, and gives them up to their own wills and wayes, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and Courſes, to do what they will with themſelves: When God deſerts his own work among a people, ſuffers his own Worſhip and Ordinances to be ineffectual, if not judicial: When God ſaith of a People, as of them, Deut. 32.20. <hi>I will hide my face from them, I will ſee what their end will be;</hi> what lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table evil end they will bring themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; and as Hoſ. 4.16. <hi>Ephraim is joined to Idols, let him alone:</hi> When God appears only as <hi>a Stranger in the Land; as a man aſtonied, a mighty man that cannot Save;</hi> Jer. 14.8. Surely then there is no hope, unleſs God magnifie his Sovereign Grace in Saving ſuch a People by himſelf.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>When the Intereſt of the World is Eſpouſed
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:47161:10"/>and Exalted; and the Intereſt of Religion is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by enpoſed, depoſed and depreſſed.</hi> When the Spirit of Worldlineſs grows exceeding high and ſtrong, and the Spirit of Religion grows low and weak, weaker and weaker, languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing even unto death; when the World pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vails againſt, and over Religion, to ſtrike it paſt ordinary hope of a Reſurrection: When the Spirit of the World, is the reigning, governing ſpirit, and carrys all before it; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can be done but in ſubſerviency to it, when it is become the Spirit of the Times; truly then all kind of Impediments and Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions to the Work of God, will become inſuperable. All Spiritual Evils, which are moſt dangerous and deſtructive, will become irreſiſtible and invincible, and the Work of Reformation, more and more impracticable and impoſſible, unleſs God undertake it by himſelf; <hi>for when the foundations are thus out of courſe, or deſtroyed, what can the Righteous do, Pſa.</hi> 11.3. at ſuch times, and in ſuch caſes as theſe, nothing but Sovereign Grace can Save us.</p>
               <p>Which is the laſt thing in the Doctrine: therefore,</p>
               <p n="5">5. It remains to be proved, <hi>That when God thus Saveth his People by himſelf, it is in Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Mercy;</hi> this is moſt evident by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in our <hi>Teaet;</hi> for when this Promiſe of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:47161:10"/>Salvation was made to <hi>Judah,</hi> and much more before it was moſt ſignally Accompliſht to them, <hi>Judah</hi> was as bad, yea worſe, more wicked than <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as was hinted before from <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.11. and is more at large ſet forth, in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.46. &amp;c. where comparing <hi>Judah</hi> with <hi>Samaria,</hi> God concludes that <hi>Judah</hi> had com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted more ſins, &amp; more abominable, than <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria;</hi> that <hi>Samaria</hi> had not <hi>committed half the ſins that Judah had;</hi> yea, that Judah was worſe than <hi>Sodom:</hi> yet God ſaith in our Text and Context, <hi>I will no more have mercy upon the Houſe of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>but will utterly take them away. But I will have mercy upon the Houſe of</hi> Judah, <hi>and will Save them by the Lord their God:</hi> this muſt needs be Sovereign Grace in the glory of it. Thus it appears, <hi>That at ſome times, and in ſome caſes, God doth in Sovereign Mercy Save his people, both from Sin and Judgment, in a more immediate and extraordinary way of work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing by himſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall pretermit what might and ought to have been ſpoken in the Application, by way of Inference, for Inſtruction, or Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition; and to proceed to the</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>EXHORTATION:</head>
               <p>Which ſpeaketh in general to all the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and Churches of <hi>NEW-ENGLAND;</hi> So
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:47161:11"/>far (at leaſt) as they may be ſpoken unto, and addreſt, in this General Aſſembly: and it is to Move, Excite and Encourage us, <hi>So to approve and apply our ſelves unto God, as he may be graciouſly moved to have mercy upon us, and to Save us by the Lord our God; (that is) to Save us in Sovereign Mercy, in a more imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate and extraordinary way of working by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let not ſuch an Exhortation be thought improper, or impertinent, to <hi>N.E.</hi> as to think or ſay within our ſelves, we hope, <hi>We are not yet come to that lamentable paſs, nor reduced to ſuch an extremity, as to be under an extream neceſſity to implore Sovereign Mercy for our Salvation; we hope our Condition is not yet ſo hopeleſs, but that we may hope to be Saved, in the ordinary way of the working of Gods Power and Mercy, by ordinary means; and therefore that it may be too much a ſcandal and reproach, to be repreſented otherwiſe as a people, utterly loſt and gone without Sovereign Mercy.</hi> O would to God, it were not ſo much ſo, as, upon ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, we may conclude it is; but we muſt underſtand, that an Apoſtatizing Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, are moſt ſecure, when they are moſt in danger, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.10. <hi>Yet ſaideſt thou not there is no hope, thou haſt found the life of thine hand, therefore thou waſt not grieved:</hi> Obſerve, an hard-hearted People will never be brought to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:47161:11"/>ſay, <hi>there is no hope,</hi> till it be too late; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore although I believe, that we are yet a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as hopeful, as to Salvation, <hi>in the iſſue,</hi> as any other viſible people of God in the World, if not more: <hi>(I ſay in the iſſue)</hi> yet thoſe who have any right underſtanding of our preſent <hi>State, Frame</hi> and <hi>Way,</hi> muſt needs acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <hi>That we have need of preſent Help and Salvation from God himſelf, working by himſelf in Sovereign Mercy;</hi> and therefore that it is our inſtant Duty and Concernment, ſo to <hi>approve and apply our ſelves unto him, as that we may obtain it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall therefore amplifie this Exhortation, by ſhewing:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>How it doth appear, that we stand in ſuch preſent need of Sovereign Mercy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>How we ought ſo to approve our ſelves to God, as that we may be prepared to be made the Subjects of it, and to recive it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>How we ought ſo to apply our ſelves to God for it, as that we may obtain it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That we may be ſenſible, that we have preſent need of ſuch Salvation from God. We may conſider:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Whether we can expect that God ſhould do any more for us in the ordinary way of the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Ordinate Power and Mercy, by ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry means, than he hath already done, to Save us;</hi> God doth put the Quaery to his People for
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:47161:12"/>Conviction: <hi>What could have been done more, that I have not done? What ſhall I do for the Danghter of my People? O Ephraim, What ſhall I do unto thee?</hi> It may not, it cannot be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied, but that God did as much in our firſt Conſtitution; <hi>(when he Planted theſe Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and Laid the Foundation of this Earth, and ſaid to</hi> New England, <hi>thou art my People</hi>) for Eſtabliſhment before him, in Faith, Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and Perſeverance under his Covenant, and in his Kingdom, and to ſecure us from Defection, and Apoſtacy from him; as we can ſay, that ever he hath done for any People theſe many Ages: Can we ſay, what God could have done more for us, to Settle us in a ſtedfaſt Standing before him, with cloſe, conſtant adherence to him, then he hath done. He choſe us, and ſet us apart to be a peculiar people to himſelf; he gave us a Conſtitution, compleated with all kind of Priviledges, Liberties, and Immunities, both Civil and Religious, which any people could deſire, enjoy or improve, unto the promotion of both Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Honeſty; he gave us a full and compleat ſtanding under his Covenant in his Kingdom, or in Church State: He gave us his Houſe, with all the Spiritual Furniture and Proviſion of it, pure Doctrine and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, the whole Goſpel Miniſtry, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:47161:12"/>the whole Faith and Order of the Goſpel, and hath hitherunto kept us in the full Poſſeſſion, Enjoyment and Improvements of all, with full Freedom, Liberty, Seaſons, Opportunities, Advantages, Encouragements, to do anything, everything, that was neceſſary for the advancement of Religion, and the intereſt and work of our <hi>Lord Chriſt,</hi> and our own Eſtabliſhment with fafety from Apoſtacy; he hath granted &amp; continued a ſpecial day of Grace, with all poſſible means of Grace, for the carrying on of the work of Converſion and Edification, and for the progreſs of all Saving Work, both in Churches and in Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies, both in Publick, and in Private: He alſo <hi>Created a Defence upon all the Glory, and appointed his Salvation for Walls and Bulwarks.</hi> What could we expect, that God could do more for us in the ordinary way of the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement of Means? Well, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all this, we have made a woful defection from God; inſomuch, that he may juſtly upbraid us, as he did them, Deut. 32.6. <hi>Do ye thus Requite the Lord your God, O fooliſh peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and unwiſe! Is not he thy Father, hath not he made thee, and eſtabliſht thee; Remember the dayes of Old; ask thy father, and he will ſhew thee, thy Elders, and they will tell thee.</hi> Now then, let us further conſider, What God could have done more for us, to recover and reſtore
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:47161:13"/>us, and bring us back again to himſelf, and this either by his <hi>Word,</hi> or by his <hi>Works.</hi> Let us Conſider,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>How much, how long, how powerfully God hath laboured with us by his Word, and by his Spirit therein.</hi> It hath been his great Work, by the Miniſtry of his Word, to awaken, convince and humble us for our Sins, by charging, judging, condemning, threatning, denouncing very dreadfully againſt us for them, by ſuch of his Servants whom he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>to cry aloud, and not to ſpare, to lift up their voices like Trumpets,</hi> in teſtifying and crying againſt thoſe Sins, and ways of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; eſpecially thoſe <hi>Heaven affrighting, aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing Sins, whereby we have ſo far exchanged our Glory, for that which profiteth not;</hi> (that is) <hi>Our God for the World,</hi> as <hi>Jer.</hi> 2 11, 12, 13. Alſo God hath by his Word, plainly propoſed and preſſed all the general Duties of the Times; wherein the work of <hi>Reformation</hi> doth conſiſt; and wherein he hath called us with utmoſt importunity, to turn unto him; moving of us by all his moſt graicous Promiſes, of all kinds of Salvations; and all this, with infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite Patience and Long Suffering, from One Generation to another; as Neh. 9.30. <hi>Yet many years didſt thou forbear them, and teſtifiedſt againſt them by thy Spirit in the Prophets, yet would they not give ear;</hi> and Zech. 7.17. <hi>But
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:47161:13"/>they refuſed to hearken, and pulled away the Shoulder, and ſtopped their Ears, that they ſhould not hear; yea, they made their hearts like an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damant Stone, leſt they ſhould hear;</hi> and from thenceforth, God gave them up to Sin and Judgment, Pſal. 81.11. <hi>But my people would not hearken to my voice, Iſrael would have none of me:</hi> By rejecting of his Word, they reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God himſelf; therefore it follows, <hi>So I gave them up to their own hearts Luſts, to walk after their own counſels: O that my People had hearkened unto me, I ſhould ſoon have ſubdued their Enemies,</hi> &amp;c. From thenceforth the Word of God became <hi>Judicial</hi> to them, Iſa. 6.10. <hi>Go make the heart of this people fat; make their ears heavy, ſhut their eyes; Leſt they ſhould Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert and be healed:</hi> God ſet them under an Hardening, Soul-killing Diſpenſation of his Word, Hoſ. 6.5. <hi>Therefore I have hewed them by the Prophets, I have ſlain them by the words of my mouth.</hi> Truly, we may with fear and trembling, conſider how generally ineffectual, the Miniſtry of the Word hath been with us, as to any general work of Converſion and Reformation, and is yet like to be; ſeeing that we cannot ſay what God could have done more for us thereby, in an ordinary way of working, to recover us, and reduce us to himſelf; So that our Lord may com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain of us, as ſometime he did of them in
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:47161:14"/>the perſon of the Prophet, Iſa. 49.4. <hi>I have Laboured in vain, I have ſpent my strength for naught and in vain.</hi> But,</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Can we ſay, what God ſhould further do further for us by his Works, to reform and ſave us; and that either by his Mercies or by his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments;</hi> and all hitherunto in vain.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Conſider how much, and how long God hath Laboured with us in a way of mercy;</hi> he hath multiplied all kinds, both of Temporal and Spiritual Mercies upon us; the richeſt, rareſt, choiceſt, peculiar mercies, the moſt alluring, obliging mercies, even loving kindneſſes and tender mercies; and if we had rightly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved them, they would have been Saving Mercies; he hath wonderfully magnified all his Mercies to us; in that they have been granted upon our Cries to him, in the times and caſes of our greateſt extremity; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued unto us notwithſtanding our great un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs, and manifold abuſes of them; they have been in all reſpects very ſignal Mercies, whereby God hath been <hi>drawing of us with the Cords of a man, the Bands of Love; Hoſ.</hi> 11.4. But, Oh how have we abuſed all theſe Mercies, to Pride, Carnal Confidence, Hardneſs of Heart, Preſumption, Security, Senſuallity; ſo that we may fear, they have been hardening, and ſo Judicial Mercies, grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not in Saving Mercy, but in Judgment.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:47161:14"/>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Conſider we further, how much, and how long God hath been Labouring with us in a way of Judgment, to reform and ſave us;</hi> he began his Proceſs with us by lighter afflictions, in a way of Chaſtiſement and Correction; he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan with the Rod, but that not availing, he Entered into Judgment, drew the Sword; and proceeded therein gradually, according as our ſins have ariſen to higher and higher de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees of Tranſgreſſion and Provocation; ſo God hath hightned the Severity of his Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and that unto a <hi>great conſumption</hi> of our ſmall people, both by the Sword, and by the Sickneſs, and otherwiſe, waſting, weaken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and conſuming of us; carrying on his whole Proceſ, in ſuch a way, as that we have been convinced and forced to confeſs, that his whole gracious deſign, thereby hath been to reform; as it is alwayes with his People, Lev. 26.23. <hi>If ye will not be reformed by theſe things,</hi> &amp;c. and the main iſſue of the whole Proceſs, is to humble and reform them, verſe 41. <hi>If then thine uncircumciſed heart be humbled, and thou accept of the puniſhment of thine Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, then will I remember my Covenant.</hi> But may not God yet complain of us, as he did of them, Jei. 44.10. <hi>They are not humbled unto this day.</hi> May we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o fear, that we are rather hardened than humbled, as they, Zeph. 3.7. <hi>I ſaid ſurely they will fear me, they will receive
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:47161:15"/>Inſtruction; but they roſe up early, and corrupted all their doings:</hi> We are under many fearful Symptoms of being hardened, and not hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, by all paſt Judgments, that we are rather the worſe than the better for them, as they, Iſa. 1.5, 6. <hi>Why ſhould ye be ſtricken any more, ye will revolt more and more; the whole head is ſick, the whole heart faint,</hi> &amp;c. and truly if ſo, we may dread that fearful Sentence, Jer. 6.29, 30. <hi>the Bellows are burnt, the Lead is conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of the Fire, the Founder melteth in vain, for the wicked are not taken away, reprobate Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhall men call them, becauſe the Lord hath rejected them:</hi> Again,</p>
               <p n="3">3. Conſider, <hi>How much and how long God hath been proving and trying of us, both by his Word, and by his Works, both by his Mercies and his Judgments; and indeed by all kind of merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Probations;</hi> to ſee whether we would re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent and reform, as he did his people of old, Deut. 8.2. <hi>to humble thee, and to prove thee, and to know what was in thy heart, whether thou wouldſt keep his Commandments or no;</hi> verſe 16. <hi>That he might humble thee, and prove thee, to do thee good in the latter end;</hi> truly ſo it is, God hath been many wayes, every way proving and trying of us, and that with much pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and long-ſuffering, waiting upon us to ſee how we would approve our ſelves unto him; it may be ſaid of this or that time, and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:47161:15"/>of this or that State and Condition; then and therein God tried and proved them; as Exod. 15.25 <hi>there he proved them,</hi> he proved them at <hi>Maſſah,</hi> Deut. 33.6. and he proved them at <hi>Meribah,</hi> Pſal. 81.7. truly ſo hath God been trying and proving <hi>New-England.</hi> It is very eaſie to Inſtance, when and how: But alas, we have not underſtood it, we do not, we will not underſtand it; and therefore it is that we have ſo wofully miſcarried and miſapproved our ſelves under all Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations; ſo that all thoſe merciful Probations, ſlighted, neglected and abuſed, have only made further diſcoveries of our Stubbornneſs, and utter averſeneſs to turn to God; and ſo our Probations have iſſued in nothing, but the further Aggravation of our Sin and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of Gods Wrath, by tempting of him. All the while God was proving of them in the Wilderneſs, they were trying and proving of him to provoke him; as Pſal. 95.8. <hi>Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den not your hearts, as in the provocation, and as in the day of temptation in the Wilderneſs, when your fathers tempted me, and proved me, and ſaw my works.</hi> All theſe things conſidered, what can we expect that God ſhould do more in an ordinary way of working for our Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and what hope of Salvation, but by the Lord our God himſelf in Sovereign Grace?</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:47161:16"/>
               <p n="2">2. To make us yet more ſenſible of our need of ſuch Salvation: We may conſider <hi>Whether we our ſelves ſhall be able to do any more for our ſelves, to Reform and Save our ſelves, than we have done.</hi> We are convinced there is no hope of Salvation without Reformation, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly we have been ſtirred to labour it in that way, by the viſible improvement of all means which we have had; all External helps, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages &amp; incouragements, unto it, both from Civil Authority (at leſt) by making all kind of Reforming Laws; as alſo, and (more eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially) by the <hi>Power and Authority of Chriſt,</hi> and that in the higheſt way of Miniſterial Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe thereof, by the Churches in Synods; declaring and teſtifying in the Name of Chriſt againſt all thoſe evils, which are the radical, and are likely to prove the fatal cauſes of our defection: &amp; laying open the whole way and work of Reformation, and propoſing Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, together with Solemn Admonitions to the People and Churches to Repent and Reform, and that upon Peril of deſtruction, if we do not. In purſuance of which we have with Extraordinary viſible Solemnity, tranſacted with God, and one with another, and therein laid our ſelves under moſt Sacred &amp; very awful Obligations, by renewed Covenant ingag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to God in Solemn manner, with Faſting, Prayer and Humiliation; wherein we have
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:47161:16"/>promiſed, vowed, profeſſed and proteſted unto him our moſt ſincere purpoſes and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions, by his Grace, to forſake our ſins, and to turn unto him with all our hearts and with all our Souls unfeignedly; and this we have been doing, until (we may fear) that we have wearyed our God, as well as our ſelves by our groſs Formalities: for ſo God ſpeaks of their higheſt formal performances, Iſa. 1.13, 14— <hi>Incenſe is an Abomination to me—Your New Mens, and appointed feaſts my Soul hateth, they de a trouble to me, I am weary to bear them.</hi> It re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains then a fearful queſtion; Whether we have not by all this Aggravated our ſins, and further accumulated Divine wrath upon our ſelves? for when a People <hi>Flatter him with their lips, and ly unto him with their tongues, heir hearts being</hi> not right with him; It provokes him to <hi>Jealouſy</hi> and to <hi>Abhorrency,</hi> Pſal. 78.3659. God ſeems to Expreſs himſelf as more grieved and provoked with the Formality, Hypociſy and Treachery of Judah, in their higheſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations, even that in Joſiahs time, than with the Idolatry of Iſrael, &amp; it haſtned deſtruction upon them; Jer. 3.10, 11. <hi>And yet for all his her treacherous Siſter Judah hath not turnes to me with her whole heart but feignedly</hi> (or in falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood) <hi>ſaith the Lord; and the Lord ſaid unto me, backſliding Iſrael, hath juſtifyed her ſelf more than treacherous Judah.</hi> What real hope is there
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:47161:17"/>then left, that we ſhall be able to doe any thing nore for our ſelves, to accompliſh our own Reformation and Salvation: Have we not caiſe then to bemoan our ſelves before and uno God, as the Church, Jer. 3.23.25. <hi>Truly in vain is Salvation hoped for from the Hills &amp;c. Truly in the Lord our God is the Salvation of Iſrael; Shame hath devoured the Labours of our Fathers,— We ly down in our Shame, that our Confuſion may cover us:</hi> and as Jer. 31.19. <hi>I have ſurely heard Ephaim</hi> bemoaning <hi>himſelf thus—Turn thou me and I ſhall be turned, for thou art the Lord my God.</hi> Thus we have heard how it doth appear that we ſtand in preſent extream need of ſuch Salvation by God himſelf in Sovereign Mecy.</p>
               <p>I Proceed,</p>
               <p n="2">2 To ſhew, <hi>how we ought ſo to approve our ſelves to God as that we may be prepared to be the Subjects of ſuch Salvation as this:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>to</hi> this end,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>
                     <hi>We muſt</hi> Labour unto a right and full underſtanding, and an humbling, heart breaking ſenſe of our own State and Condition, that we may lay it deeply to heart.</hi> It was the ruine of Gods People, that would never be made to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, nor lay to heart, of which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains, Iſa. 1.3. <hi>Iſrael doth not know, my Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple doth not conſider;</hi> and yet it was at ſuch a time, wherein <hi>the whole head was ſick, and the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:47161:17"/>whole heart faint; from the ſole of the foot to the head, there was nothing but wounds, and brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and putrifying ſores, which had not been clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, nor bound up, nor mollified with Oyntment:</hi> Yet even then they did not <hi>Know</hi> nor <hi>Conſider</hi> what their Condition was; ſo Iſa. 42.25. <hi>It ſet him on fire round about, yet he knew not; it conſumed him, yet he laid it not to heart;</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they could not be Saved, becauſe they would not lay it to heart, Jer. 12.11. <hi>The whole Land is Deſolate, becauſe no man layeth to heart:</hi> Surely, there is very little ſign of any laying to heart in <hi>New-England,</hi> but the quite contrary; as it was with them, Iſa. 22.12, 13. <hi>In that day did the Lord God of Hoſts call to weeping and mourning, and baldneſs, and gird<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with Sackcloth; and behold joy and gladneſs, ſlaying of Oxen, and killing of Sheep, eating fleſh, and drinking Wine. It was revealed in mine ear by the Lord of Hoſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>urely this Iniquity ſhall not be purged yrom you, till ye die.</hi> God grant that <hi>New-England</hi> may never incur this dreadful Sentence. We are much in the <hi>Laodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean</hi> State and Frame; conceited that <hi>we are rich, and increaſed with Goods, and know not that we are poor and blind, &amp; wretched &amp; miſerable, &amp; naked, Rev.</hi> 3.17. It is the great thing that God is labouring to bring us to, that we may underſtand and lay to heart, Deut. 32.29. <hi>O that they were wiſe, that they underſtood theſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:47161:18"/>things, that they would conſider their Latter End.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>
                     <hi>We muſt</hi> utterly renounce all carnal confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in our ſelves, or in any arm of Fleſh;</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially thoſe carnal confidences, which we are moſt apt unto, and which are moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; thoſe carnal confidences in our viſible Covenant-relation to God, in our viſible Church-State, the viſible Priviledges, Intereſts and Enjoyments of the Houſe of God; to cry as they, Jer. 7.4. <hi>The Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord.</hi> Carnal Confidence in our own Faith, and Prayer, is yet more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous to think as they ſpake, Iſa. 58.3. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have we faſted ſay they, and thou ſeeſt not, and afflicted our Souls, and thou takeſt no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge?</hi> It is divers ways too evident, that we have abuſed our Faith and Prayer too much, to carnal confidence; but that which is moſt dangerous and deſtructive, is, carnal confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in God h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>elf, Mic. 3.11. <hi>Yet will they lean upon the Lord, and ſay, is not the Lord among us, none evil can come upon us; therefore ſhall</hi> Zion <hi>for your ſakes be plowed like a field:</hi> If ever we hope to be Saved in Sovereign Mercy by the Lord our God himſelf, we muſt away with all our carnal confidences, and Pray as the Church, Hoſ. 14.3. <hi>Take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Iniquity, and receive us graciouſly— Aſhur ſhall not Save us;— for in thee the fatherleſs find mercy.</hi> We muſt become as <hi>fatherleſs;</hi> then
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:47161:18"/>God promiſeth, as ver. 4. <hi>I will heal their Backſlidings, I will love them freely;</hi> we muſt become <hi>a poor and an afflicted people,</hi> Zeph. 3.11, 12. <hi>For then I will take away out of the midſt of thee, them that rejoice in thy pride, and thou ſhalt no more be haughty, becauſe of my Holy Mountain: I will leave in the midſt of thee, an afflicted</hi> and poor people; and then it follows ver. 15. <hi>The Lord hath taken away thy Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, he hath caſt out the Enemy;</hi> ver. 17. <hi>The Lord thy God in the midſt of thee, is mighty, he will Save; When God ſeeth that all power is gone, and that there is none ſhut up nor left;</hi> then then they are prepared for Salvation in Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Mercy, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.36. When a people ſpeak <hi>trembling, and out of the duſt,</hi> that is, out of a depth of Humiliation, then they are prepared for this Sovereign Mercy, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.1.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>We muſt</hi> Labour <hi>to underſtand what it is to be Saved by the Lord our God; what it is that God muſt work both in us, and for us, to Save us: what Salvation is,</hi> what our own Saving Good and Welfare is; ignorance of this doth make a people uncapable of Salvation, Hoſea 11.3. <hi>They knew not that I healed them;</hi> this Ignorance was that which our Lord lamented with tears, weeping over Jeruſalem, Luke 19.41. <hi>If thou hadſt known, even thou at leaſt in this thy day, the things of thy peace, but now they are hid from thine eyes.</hi> God grant that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:47161:19"/>this may not be verified on <hi>New-England,</hi> of which there are very ſad ſigns; we muſt therefore ſet our hearts upon that which is and will be our Salvation; and without which there can be no Salvation; <hi>(viz.)</hi> the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful progreſs of the Word, Worſhip and Work of God; the Converſion of our Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the Reformation of our Churches, the Reſurrection of Religion: O if our heart were ſet upon theſe things, we ſhould be heartily willing to be Saved, earneſtly deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to be Saved; and if we were ſo, God would ſoon Save us; Iſa. 1.19. <hi>If ye be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling:</hi> But ſo it is, an Apoſtatizing People de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practically refuſe to be Saved, Iſa. 30.15. <hi>For thus ſaith the Lord, in returning and in reſt ſhal ye be Saved, in quietneſs and confidence ſhall be your Strength; and ye would not, but ye ſaid no</hi> &amp;c. Jer. 2.25. <hi>but thou ſaidſt, there is no hope we have loved Strangers, and after them we wil go;</hi> This alſo our Lord laments, <hi>Mat.</hi> 23.37 <hi>O Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem; how often would I have gathered thy Children, and ye would not; behold your houſe is left unto you deſolate.</hi> God never deſtroyes his people, but they wilfully refuſe to be Saved; truly our wilfulneſs in thoſe ways of ſinning, which are the direct and broad way to deſtruction; is fearfully ſigna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to us: God hath been healing of us, and we will not be healed, we will not be Saved from
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:47161:19"/>our ſins, but ſeem to be the more reſolute in them, Hoſ. 7.1. <hi>When I would have healed Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, then the Iniquity of Ephraim, &amp; the wickedneſs of Samaria, was diſcovered;</hi> truly that the ſins of the times with us, not only continue but prevail more &amp; more; notwithſtanding all, that God hath been doing to Save us from them; is matter of fearful conſideration to us, and deep Humiliation, to all who have any ſence of the State and Condition of our People and Churches: O that we knew what it is to be Saved.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>
                     <hi>We muſt</hi> ſubmit and commit our ſelves unto God, with a practical acknowledgment of, and ſubjection unto his abſolute Soveraignty, as alſo to the Supremacy of his Wiſdom and Will;</hi> that whatſoever he doth, it is good, yea, it is beſt in it ſelf, and as he doth it; and withal giving of him the glory of all that he doth to us or for us, or with us, whether in mercy or in Judgment, with an abſolute ſubmiſſion to his Soveraign Will and Pleaſure, and an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſolution to bear and indure whatſoever he ſhall pleaſe to inflict; be willing he ſhould take any courſe with us to Save us; withal acknowledging our unworthineſs of ſuch Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; thus the people, Judg. 10.15. <hi>We have ſinned, do with us what ſeemeth good to thee, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver us only we pray thee this day:</hi> Obſerve here how they Implore Sovereign Mercy for their
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:47161:20"/>Salvation; and caſt themſelves into the arms of it; and it follows, ver. 16. <hi>his Soul was grieved for the miſery of Iſrael;</hi> and ſo inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Saved them by himſelf.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>
                     <hi>We muſt</hi> ariſe and ſet to work for God;</hi> with utmoſt labour, diligence, zeal, courage, faithfulneſs, with all our hearts and Souls, with all our might and ſtrength, with a moſt ſincere and fervent love to the work of God, and an heart, care, and concernment for it; as long as we ſit ſtill, and ſlight and neglect and deſert the Work of God; running every man to his own houſe, as they, Hag. 1.9. that is, giving up our ſelves to the World, and Worldlineſs; ſo long as <hi>all ſeek their own things and not the things which are Jeſus Chriſts,</hi> Phil. 2.21. I ſay, ſo long as it is thus, there is no hope that God will work for us in ſuch an extraordinary way of Salvation: But if we will ariſe and work for, and with God, God will ariſe, and work for, and with us; Hag. 2.4, 5. <hi>Now be ſtrong</hi> O Zerubbabel, <hi>and be ſtrong,</hi> O Joſhua, <hi>and be ſtrong all ye people of the Land, and work, for I am with you,—and my Spirit remaineth among you, fear not.</hi> Obſerve, if we will work, God will be with us, and carry on all Saving Work for us by his Spirit. Falſeneſs, Unfaithfulneſs, Unſtedfaſtneſs in the Work of God, doth render us not only
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:47161:20"/>unworthy and unfit, but utterly uncapable of ſuch Salvation.</p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>
                     <hi>We muſt</hi> hearken moſt intenſely and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,</hi> ſubjecting our very Souls to the Word of God; which is the higheſt means of the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Divine Wiſdom, Power, Grace and Mercy in all Saving Work for the Children of men: Yea, and in working all kind of Salvations for the Church and People of God. The whole glorious work of Salvation out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> was wrought by the Word, Hoſ. 12.13. <hi>By a Prophet the Lord brought Iſrael out of Egypt, and by a Prophet he preſerved them;</hi> by the Miniſtry of his Word he Saved them out of their Apoſtacy, and the Calamity of the Babyloniſh Captivity; as appears by the whole Hiſtory of <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies of <hi>Zechariah</hi> and <hi>Haggai;</hi> and by the Miniſtry of the Word, the great and laſt Salvation for the Church ſhall be wrought; Iſa. 52.6, 7. <hi>How beautiful upon the Mountains are the feet of him, that bringeth good tidings, that publiſheth peace, that bringeth good tydings of good, that publiſheth Salvation, that ſaith to</hi> Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>thy God reigneth.</hi> Our Lord alſo propheſieth the ſame, Mat. 23.39. <hi>For I ſay unto you, ye ſhall not ſee me henceforth, till ye ſhall ſay, bleſſed is he that cometh in the Name of the Lord:</hi> Surely, it was by the Miniſtry of the Word, that God wrought gloriouſly for <hi>New-England,</hi> in giving
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:47161:21"/>of us our Being, as his People. It is by the Miniſtry of his Word that he upholds and carries on the work of Converſion, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by upholds his Churches in their Spiritual Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Conſtitution, and Religion in them; and therefore it muſt be by the Miniſtry of his Word, that that Work, and theſe Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and Religion which are now ſinking and dying, muſt be recovered and revived, by a thorough Saving Reformation. It is by the power of the Word, that God makes Mercies and Judgments, and all other Providential Diſpenſations, even all his wayes and works unto his people ſaving; nothing will do us good, till God work by his Word, to make all effectual. It is by his Word, that he doth lead and guide his people into, and in the way of Salvation: It is by his Word that he removes all obſtructions, ſubdues all oppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that the <hi>great Mountains before</hi> Zerubba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel, <hi>become a Plain,</hi> Zech. 4.7. It is by his Word that he doth ſtir up, and ſtrengthen all Inſtruments, quicken, ſanctifie and ſpirit all his Servants to his work. O when God comes to Save <hi>New-England</hi> by himſelf, we ſhall ſee and feel wonderful effects &amp; changes wrought by the Miniſtry of the Word; and when once our hearts are fully &amp; generally ſubject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the power of the Word, then we may be aſſured, that God is ariſen, and at work
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:47161:21"/>for us in a glorious way of Salvation by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; then we ſhall be prepared to be the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of ſuch Salvation: When our hearts tremble under the power of the Word, as it was with them, when God was at work with them, to reform them, Ezra 9.4. <hi>Then were aſſembled to me, every one that trembled at the words of the God of Iſrael;</hi> and again, <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.3. <hi>According to the counſel of my Lord, and of thoſe that tremble at the Commandment of our God:</hi> God would do nothing for them till they did thus ſubject themſelves to his Word, Zech. 7.7. <hi>Should ye not hear the words which the Lord hath cried by the voice of the former Prophets, whilſt Jeruſalem was inhabited.</hi> Surely God expects that <hi>New-England</hi> ſhould hear and obey thoſe many ſolemn words which he hath cried to them by the voice of the former Prophets, as well as thoſe which he is ſtill crying unto us by the preſent Miniſtry, and this we muſt do before we can upon any grounds of Faith and Hope, expect that God ſhould Save us by himſelf: Thus we ought to approve our ſelves unto God.</p>
               <p>I Proceed,</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>To ſhew how we ought to apply our ſelves to God for ſuch Salvation;</hi> and this I need not tell you, we all know it muſt be by Faith and Prayer.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>By Faith,</hi> and it muſt be Pure Faith,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:47161:22"/>without the leaſt mixture or tincture of carnal Confidence, Prefidence or Diffidence; and our Faith muſt work under a moſt humbling ſence of our ſins and of our unworthineſs, and of our own utter inſufficiency to help our ſelves, and our preſent Extream neceſſity of help from God, and from God alone, and that with a full reliance and recumbence upon him, and an high and ſtrong Confidence in him for ſuch Salvation; with an humble and yet firm dependence upon his Infinite Sufficiency, and his Sovereign Grace and Mercy; and with an hopeful, patient, earneſt, inſtant Expectation, looking, longing, waiting and watching for him in this way of Salvation. Thus we muſt believe by Faith, Aſſerting our Covenant inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt in him and relation unto him as our God, the God of our Salvation; as the Church <hi>Iſa.</hi> 25.9. <hi>Lo this is our God, we have waited for him, he will ſave us; this is the Lord we have waited for him, we will rejoyce and he glad in his Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>With ſuch an exerciſe of Faith we are to apply unto God by Prayer:</hi> for ſuch Faith works moſt powerfully and effectually, by Prayer; and is ever prevalent with God, never fails, but ever obtains help from God; but then we muſt pray indeed, Pray in good earneſt, with utmoſt Sincerity, Fervency, Inſtancy, Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity, labouring therein even unto an Agony:
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:47161:22"/>not only cry, but cry mightily, with an out-cry of Prayer, as a People ready to periſh: as the Children of Iſrael at the Red-Sea; <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.10. <hi>The People of Iſrael Cryed out to the Lord.</hi> Truly we are now concerned to Pray as for our Lives; yea much more than for our own Lives, by the utmoſt improvement of all Arguments of Faith and Hope in pleading with God: Striv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as it were once for all; reſolving with Wreſtling <hi>Jacob,</hi> that through his Grace, and by his own ſtrength, we will <hi>Hold him, and not let him go</hi> till we obtain; as Remembering that we are Praying and Crying for Sovereign Mercy; and being ſenſible, that not only the eternal concernments of our own Souls, but that all the Saving concernments of our Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and People, and of all Poſterity: that our very being and ſtanding before God under his Covenant, in his Kingdom as his People: Yea that all the concernments of Gods own Cauſe, Intereſt, Name and Glory, with us, have great dependance upon the ſucceſs of our Prayers at this time: God hath been labouring long to make <hi>New-England</hi> cry. God doth Expect &amp; Wait to hear us cry to him, as <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.14. <hi>Wilt thou not at this time cry to me, my Father, thou art the guide of my youth:</hi> &amp; he hath promiſed that he will be very gracious to the Voice of our cry, that when he doth hear it, he will anſwer, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.19. Truly it is much to be feared, that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:47161:23"/>
                  <hi>New-England</hi> doth not yet know what it is to cry; that is with Lamenting, Bemoaning, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wailing, Deploring, Mournful, Penitential Crys of Prayer; although there are a Praying Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple yet left with us, thoſe who are Gods Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrancers, who ſtand before him in the <hi>Gap.</hi> But alas, how much of the Spirit, Life and Power of Prayer, is decayed and wanting, among People and Profeſſors, in Publick, Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate &amp; Secret; and how much we have failed and falſifyed with God in our Prayers: We have ſad cauſe to Conſider, O that there might be ſuch a General, Powerful cry of Prayer as ſometimes there hath been with us; and as God now expects and looks for, and which is abſolutely neceſſary, as the way and means wherein we are to ſeek and labour to obtain this Salvation from God: God hath therefore promiſed, that his People ſhall pray, <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.11, 12. <hi>Then ſhall ye call upon me, and ye ſhall goe and Pray unto me, and I will hearken unto you, and yee ſhall ſeek me and find me, when ye ſhall ſearch for me with all your heart:</hi> This is a promiſe that then they ſhould Pray when the time of Salvation was come. God alwayes Saves his People in the way of Prayer, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.9. <hi>They ſhall come with Weeping and with Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication will I lead them.</hi> Oh that God would pour out the Spirit of Grace &amp; Supplication upon us!</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:47161:23"/>
               <p>But it may be inquired, <hi>What we are more eſpecially and particularly to Believe and Pray for, in order to the Obtainment of ſuch Salvation?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I Reply, <hi>It muſt be for the returns and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of the Divine Preſence, and the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Promiſe of the Spirit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>That God would no further or longer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw himſelf;</hi> His Spiritual, Gracious &amp; Saving Preſence, but return to us in thoſe ways and by thoſe degrees wherein and whereby he hath been departing from us: We have yet all the viſible ſigns and means of his preſence, that ever we had, or any People can have: But alas, how much have we loſt of the Spiritual Beauty, Glory, Power, Saving Effects, and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs of his preſence, and of the comfortable Beatifical Apprehenſions of his preſence in Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Communion with him and communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations from him. God is much with-drawn from our hearts, and from his own Houſe; much of the Protecting, Directing, Proſpering, Propitious preſence of God, in the wayes of his Providence gone. And truly the Divine preſence ſeems ſtill to be upon its remove from us; &amp; we &amp; our People ſeem to be very little ſenſible of it, and growing more inſenſible &amp; unconcerned about it: ſurely then it is high time for us to ſtir up our ſelves to take hold of God: we may complain with the Church, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 64.7. <hi>There is none that call upon thy Name,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:47161:24"/>that ſtirreth up himſelf, to take hold of thee, for thou haſt hid thy face from us and conſumed us:</hi> Hoſ. 10.12. <hi>It is time to ſeek the Lord till he come;</hi> that is till he return. Truly, Wo will be to us, if we ſuffer God to depart quite away from us! <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 9.12. It was therefore the burthen of the Churches Prayer, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 80.3.7.19—Cauſe <hi>thy face to ſhine upon us and we ſhall be Saved:</hi> More plainly Expreſſed, Verſe 14. <hi>Return O Lord we beſeech thee.</hi> When ever God Saves his People, he returns; and when ever he returns, he brings Salvation with him, <hi>Zech.</hi> 1.16. <hi>I am returned to Jeruſalem with great Mercies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>We muſt believe and pray for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the great Promiſe of the Spirit.</hi> It was intimated before, that God works more imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately to Save his People by his Spirit; they therefore can expect no ſuch Salvation, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then by the accompliſhment of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the Spirit; which indeed ſeems to be a Fundamental Article of the Covenant of Grace; becauſe it is by the performance of that he brings his People into Covenant with himſelf, and applies all the Saving Grace of the Covenant unto them, and ſo thereby he becomes their God, and makes them his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; therefore it is ſo often in expreſs terms given and renewed in the Scripture, both of the Old and New Teſtament, as Iſa. 44.1, 6. Iſa. 59.20, 21. Ezek. 36.27. Ezek. 37.14.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:47161:24"/>Ezek. 39.29. Joel 2.28. and elſewhere abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly; which ſignifies, that God hath laid this Promiſe of his Spirit in the foundation of the Faith, Hope and Confidence of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and that the accompliſhment of it, is the great thing which they are to believe and pray for, in order to their Salvation; and therefore he hath directed his Church to wait upon him for Salvation, until he pour out his Spirit, Iſa. 32.15. <hi>Until the Spirit be poured upon us from on high, and the Wilderneſs become a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful field.</hi> There were gracious Promiſes of Salvation made to the Church in that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text; but they were to wait for it, until the Spirit was poured upon them from on high: It all depended upon the accompliſhment of the Promiſe of the Spirit. We have (it may be) ſometimes thought and hoped, that we had ſeen God working in the way of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, at this time, and at that, for our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; and we have been apt to be much rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in our Spirits with what we have ſo thought God hath been doing for us, and that with very high hopes of being ſuddenly and perfectly reſtored to as good and happy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as ever. But alas! do we ſee, do we feel God working by the power of his Spirit? Truly, if not, whatever other Signs or Prog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſticks of good we may think we ſee, we may aſſure our ſelves, that all ſuch hopes and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:47161:25"/>confidences will fail us, and we ſhall be left to complain with the Church, Jer. 14.19. <hi>We looked for peace, but no good hath come, for a time of healing, and behold trouble;</hi> and as Iſa. 59.9, 11. <hi>We wait for light, and behold obſcurity, for brightneſs, but we walk in darkneſs:— We looked for Judgment, but there is none, for Salvation, but it is far from us.</hi> Thus it will be, ſo long as God doth with hold and ſuſpend the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation of the Spirit, which is of all other, the moſt humbling conſideration of our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſtate and condition; and therefore, if we hope that God ſhould ever have mercy upon <hi>New-England,</hi> and Save us by himſelf; we muſt labour our very Souls muſt labour, by Faith in Prayer, for the accompliſhment of the Promiſe of the Spirit. It is by the accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhment of this Promiſe, that God doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh all other Promiſes and Propheſies al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to his Church, referring to their Salvation: Yea, it is by the accompliſhment of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of the Spirit, that he doth accompliſh all his moſt great and Glorious Works in the World, referring more directly to his own Kingdom, Name and Glory. O may we ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this Diſpenſation of the Spirit, then his will be filled with his Spirit; whereby the Miniſtry and Miniſtration of it will be made mighty and powerful, as the <hi>Rod of Christs Strength ſent out of</hi> Zion, and we ſhall be made
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:47161:25"/>a <hi>willing people in ſuch a day of his Power,</hi> Pſal. 110.2, 3. Then all Ordinances ſhall be filled with the Spirit, and ſo become, powerful and effectual, unto the moſt full and abundant com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication of all ſaving grace and bleſſing; repreſented in the Viſion of the Candleſtick, by the two living, growing, Olive Trees or Branches; diſtilling the Golden Oyl into the Pipes; ſignifying, the Spirit powerfully work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the communication of Grace &amp; Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, by the Adminiſtration of Ordinances; therefore the Viſion was expounded by the Promiſe of the Spirit, Zech. 4.6. Alſo God by filling his Word and Ordinances with his Spirit, will fill his Churches with his Spirit; &amp; then we ſhall ſee the Churches ſpirited unto Church Reformation; and ſo flouriſhing again with all Spiritual Proſperity: the Promiſe, it is primarily made unto the Churches; by the accompliſhment of which, God will alſo fill all his Servants, (betruſted with the management of the affairs of his People and Churches) with his Spirit. Yea, all his people will be graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly influenced by his Spirit, unto extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Ability and Activity in his Service. O that we may thus believe and pray effectually, that God would, <hi>Pour out his Spirit upon all Fleſh,</hi> according to his Promiſe, <hi>Joel</hi> 2.28, 29. Eſpecially reſpecting the ſaving gifts &amp; graces of it, in a general work of Converſion where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:47161:26"/>more eſpecially it is that God works more immediately, to Save his People by himſelf, and which is, the only true and real Salvation. And when God thus pours out his Spirit upon his People and Churches, he works alſo in an extraordinary way, and manner, by his Spirit, in the ways and works of his Providence, eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially with reference to his Church; which is held forth to us, in that Viſional Scheme of Divine Providence, Ezek. 1. <hi>By the Spirit of the Living Creatures, and the Wheeles, and the Throne, and the appearance of a man upon it;</hi> ſignifying, our Lord Chriſt, in the Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of his Providential Kingdom, by the working of his Spirit in the Diſpenſations of Providence; a more glorious appearance of which, will be ſeen in approaching accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Hence we proceed to the</p>
               <p n="2">2 Exhortation: <hi>Which is to Excite us to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, apply and improve this great Promiſe, that God will have mercy upon</hi> New-England, <hi>and Save us by himſelf.</hi> Not by might, nor by power, but by his Spirit, and that in a way of Sovereign Grace; this ſeems to be the only hopeful way that we have left, wherein God calls us to wait upon him for Salvation. O therefore that we may obtain grace ſo to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, apply and improve this Promiſe, and thereby enter into this moſt ſure and happy way of Salvation. Therefore</p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:47161:26"/>
               <p n="1">1. I take leave humbly to propoſe this Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, <hi>unto thoſe who are, or may be our Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, together with the Repreſentatives of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in this General Aſſembly.</hi> Right Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, much Honoured and Reſpected, <hi>Suffer your ſelves to be intreated, in the Name of the Lord, and by this Word of the Lord; to undertake, and carry on your whole work, in the Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Government, both by Legiſlation and Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, and in the management of all the great Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the Publick Weal of this People of God, which you are by him betruſted withal, by a very powerful exerciſe of Faith, in this great Promiſe, that God will have mercy upon this his People, and Save them, by the Lord their God:</hi> This is the Word of the Lord to you, as it was to <hi>Zerubbabel,</hi> the Governour of <hi>Judah; Not by might, nor by power, but by my Spirit ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</hi> It remains as ſure a founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Faith to you, as it was to him: Thoſe whom God made Rulers and Deliverers of his People; eſpecially in times and caſes of Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty and Danger; they are Chronicled <hi>in Holy Writ, for mighty men of Faith,</hi> according to the Apoſtles Induction, Heb. 11. <hi>Moſes, Gide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Barak, Sampſon, Jeptha, David, Samuel;</hi> to whom we may add, <hi>Joſhua, Ezra, Nehemiah, Zerubbabel:</hi> Theſe all carried on their mighty works, for the Salvation of Gods People, by Faith; and therefore were ſtyled Saviours,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:47161:27"/>
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.7. <hi>According to thy manifold mercies, thou gaveſt them Saviours, who Saved them.</hi> If God ſhall ſo ſpirit You unto believing, we ſhall be comfortably perſwaded, if not aſſured, that he will make you ſuch Saviours, and Save us by your means: The preſent State of our People, in this difficult, diſtreſſing conjuncture of time and affairs, doth require the extraordinary ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe and improvement of your Faith in God, according to this promiſe; nothing can be done effectually by you for our Salvation without it; every thing will be ſavingly performed by it. May you, by the Exerciſe of Faith in Prayer, obtain the accompliſhment of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to your ſelves; you ſhall by an inexpreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Experiment, feel the Spirit of God coming upon you, moving and actuating of you, by the more immediate influences of his Divine Wiſdom, Power and Grace, in all Service un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, and his People, in your ſeveral places, and that with a ſincere and ſingle reſpect, to his Glory, and our good, which is the higheſt good and end of all Government. And then you ſhall be ſtirred up &amp; ſtrengthened, to ſet your ſelves, with an high and holy zeal and courage, in the <hi>Strength and Power of the Spirit of God,</hi> againſt all the moſt powerful, dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and deſtructive Sins and Evils of the Times. The Spirit of God ſhall by you, <hi>Lift up a Standard againſt them;</hi> now they are brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:47161:27"/>in upon us <hi>like a Flood.</hi> It appears by Scripture Inſtances, that it is Gods way to Save his People from their Sins, by the <hi>power and working of his Spirit, in and by Religious Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,</hi> as well as in and by his Word, &amp; <hi>ſeldome otherwiſe.</hi> In the power of the Spirit alſo, you ſhall labour effectually to recover, uphold and advance Religion, by promoting Holineſs and Righteouſneſs, in all the wayes of it; that ſo we may live quiet and peaceable lives in all Godlineſs and Honeſty. Much Honoured, I do with all humble Importunity, Pray &amp; Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you, to ſuffer this word of Exhortation. It will be your higheſt honour, as well as hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs in your Station, to Subſerve ſo immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately by the Spirit unto God himſelf, when he comes to Saves his People by himſelf. The firſt <hi>New England</hi> Magiſtracy, under whoſe Conduct, God led his People into this Land; by Faith obtained this Promiſe of the Spirit; and being extraordinarily (even divinely) Spirited, both in the undertaking and progreſs of that glorious work, unto an happy conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, in Setting up Churches, Worſhip, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances, and the Spiritual Kingdom of Chriſt here. May it therefore be your higheſt, and very holy ambition, to be (through the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and aſſiſtance of the Spirit) Repairers and Reſtorers of that work, and of theſe Churches thereby unto their primitive beauty and holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:47161:28"/>&amp; that more eſpecially at ſuch a time, wherein God ſeems to be ariſen unto an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary way of working, in preparation unto great Accompliſhments for his Churches and People in the World. Herein you ſhall not only be graciouſly <hi>accepted,</hi> but gloriouſly <hi>Rewarded;</hi> for if God thus improve you, and you thus approve your ſelves unto God, he will <hi>Signalize</hi> his ſpecial favour unto you, by making and ſetting of you as a <hi>Signet</hi> upon his right hand, <hi>Hag.</hi> 2. <hi>ult.</hi> Then ſhall we with much joy and thankfulneſs, acknowledge to his Praiſe, That he hath given us Rulers <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinely Spirited Juſt men, fearing God; and that he hath restored unto us our Judges as at the firſt, and our Counſellors as at the Beginning.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. I propoſe the ſame word of Exhortation <hi>unto my Brethren in the Miniſtry,</hi> and herein I deſire firſt to apply to my ſelf, who am among all the reſt moſt unworthy; &amp; therefore moſt unmeet in that reſpect to apply unto you; yet having (through divine patience and mercy) lived to out-live the moſt of thoſe of the more worthy Servants of Chriſt, who have been Coaetaneous with me, and being one of thoſe Ancient Men yet Surviving, who have ſeen the <hi>Firſt Temple, the Firſt Houſe,</hi> in much of its <hi>Firſt Glory:</hi> I mean theſe Churches, ſhining with the fulneſs and ſplendor of the divine preſence, in the beauty of holineſs; and who
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:47161:28"/>have alſo unhappily ſeen, the beginning and progreſs of that defection, which hath occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned the gradual removes of the Glory, and which doth endanger, the diſſolution of their Conſtitution; therefore I ought to be the more ſenſible, and deeply affected, &amp; to propoſe &amp; preſs the Exhortation the more ſenſibly and affectionately. Whereby, O that we might be all moved, <hi>to wait earnestly upon God by Faith in Prayer, for the Promiſe of the Spirit in the more full accompliſhment of it to our ſelves:</hi> We (tho unworthy) are Servants of our Lord Chriſt, under peculiar relation unto him, as <hi>the great Prophet, Apoſtle, Shepherd and Biſhop of Souls, the head Miniſter of this moſt glorious Goſpel Miniſtry and Ministration;</hi> who hath en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged himſelf to his Servants, by many ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Promiſes, of his Preſence, Spirit, Power, and Grace, to carry on his own work in their hands, more immediately <hi>by himſelf,</hi> in reſpect of which it is ſaid; <hi>They are Labourers together with God, and to work the work of the Lord,</hi> that which is more peculiarly his; unto which, no Creature in Heaven or Earth, hath any <hi>Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſufficiency,</hi> and wherein <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Apollos</hi> them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves were <hi>nothing;</hi> and in which the <hi>Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of Power, doth alwayes appear to be of God:</hi> And becauſe it is all Spiritual, Supernatural &amp; Creating Work; Wherein the Apoſtle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, ſaid he, laboured, <hi>with fear &amp; much trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling:</hi>
                  <pb n="52" facs="tcp:47161:29"/>doubtleſs under awful apprehenſions of the more immediate Acceſſes and Concourſes of the Divine Preſence and Power: nothing therefore is to be done in it Savingly, but by Divine Sufficiency, ingaged by the Spirit, by whom his Servants may be <hi>endued with power from on high, and made able Miniſters of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, the Holy Ghoſt being ſent down from Heaven, together with the Word Preached,</hi> by their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. The means whereby this work is to be carried on, are not <hi>Carnal, but Spiritual and Mighty,</hi> only <hi>through God:</hi> and ſo are to be improved only through Faith, that his Servants being <hi>full of Faith, may alſo be full of the Holy Ghoſt, and of Power.</hi> God gave a very pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful, proſperous progreſs to this glorious work by the Firſt <hi>Old England</hi> Miniſtry in the firſt <hi>New England</hi> Churches, which flouriſhed ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly thereby. And God hath graciouſly upheld it by the ſucceeding Miniſtry, though not with like fulneſs of ſaving ſucceſs. Nor without a very fadening, humbling diminition of Saving Grace and Bleſſing, and a gradual failure of the work of Converſion. The work being therefore attended, with more &amp; more difficulty and diſcouragement. O how much the more are the poor Servants of Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to reinforce and ſtrengthen their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendence upon him, by Faith in his Promiſe, (in all the Promiſes) of his Spirit for more immediate and extraordinary Aſſiſtance, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:47161:29"/>they are called to labour for him in the decaying State of Religion, the declining State of Churches and Chriſtians, with a Back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliding people, with an hard-hearted, unbeliev<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, diſobedient generation of Sinners, height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ſtrengthning themſelves in their ways of ſinning, multiplying and aggravating all the Sins of the Times, unto an higher and higher degree, both of Tranſgreſſion and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation; and much in danger of falling un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that moſt dreadful Execution of Divine Vindictive Juſtice upon the Souls of men, by Spiritual Plagues and Judgments. And in all this to ſtand before, and miniſter unto, <hi>an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry and departing God, proceeding in a way of Judgment;</hi> and before our Lord Chriſt, who is ſo far <hi>provoked,</hi> as to threaten, <hi>to come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, to remove the Candleſtick out of its place, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept we ſpeedily repent, and do the firſt works:</hi> O then with how much <hi>Soul concern,</hi> ought all thoſe who have received this Miniſtry, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore divine mercy that they may not faint; but may obtain Faith to perſevere, with cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and confidence, under <hi>the working of his Power, which may work in them more immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and mightily by the Spirit,</hi> to furniſh them more abundantly with the Spirit and Grace of the Goſpel Miniſtry. That they may <hi>ſpeak as the Oracles of God;</hi> all that which God would have ſpoken unto his people, at ſuch a time, and in ſuch a caſe, which may be moſt ſuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:47161:30"/>ſeaſonable, powerful and effectual to awaken, convince, admoniſh, warn, inſtruct, exhort, humble; to deliver all the Meſſages, which God doth ſend, even the <hi>whole burthen of the Word of the Lord, to hear and receive the Word from his mouth, and ſo to warn the people from him, that they may deliver their own Souls.</hi> O never, never, hath there been ſo great an incumbency upon any <hi>New England</hi> Miniſtry; as upon this Miniſtry which God hath now raiſed up: (and through his grace hopefully qualified) to labour with the preſent riſing and ſtanding Generations in theſe Churches; forasmuch as our <hi>Weal or Wo, in the iſſue of Gods Controverſy with us, either in Mercy or in Judgment, either in Salvation or Deſtruction, will have great dependance upon the ſucceſsfulneſs, or unſucceſsfulneſs of this Miniſtry.</hi> If God make this Miniſtry ſavingly ſucceſsful in a general Converſion, <hi>we are Saved:</hi> If God ſuffer it to be Judicial, <hi>we may tremble with fear, at the thoughts of the iſſue;</hi> inaſmuch as this Miniſtry ſeems to be ſet for the <hi>laſt Tryal or Probation (at leaſt) of that Generation, with whom God hath been, and is in a way of Judgment</hi> O then, Let us be moved to believe and pray powerfully for ſuch of the Servants of Chriſt, who are <hi>juſt now</hi> Entred or Entring upon the Work of the Miniſtry; and who are to labour therein, under every <hi>dark and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:47161:30"/>doubtful Diſpenſations, not knowing what God will do with his People and Churches here.</hi> Oh, who may Survive or live to ſee <hi>the iſſues and events, either in Salvation, or otherwiſe?</hi> I ſay, Let us Believe and Pray for them, that they may lay out themſelves, their very Hearts and Souls in every part of their work: and that their Miniſtry may be ſavingly ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful; and themſelves eminently Subſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, <hi>to a Glorious Salvation by the Lord our God Himſelf, in a way of Sovereign Grace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To Conclude,</p>
               <p n="3">3 I propoſe this Exhortation, <hi>To all the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving Praying People of God with us.</hi> O believe and pray; Improve this great promiſe by Faith in Praver, That God may have mercy upon <hi>New-England,</hi> and Save us by himſelf in a way of Sovereign Grace. It is high time thus to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and pray: and to this end,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>We muſt</hi> take heed, that we do not preſume upon Sovereign Grace, which we are apt and (I fear we begin) to doe: We muſt therefore remember that God hath not by his Covenant abſolutely ingaged the abſolute ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency of his Sovereign Grace for the Salvation of his people; but he hath ingaged himſelf only according to the Ordinate &amp; Ordinary work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Grace and Mercy, to a repenting, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, obedient, reforming People. God is not wont to Save an hard hearted, Impenitent, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>believing,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:47161:31"/>diſobedient People continuning in their ſins, ſlighting, neglecting, abuſing &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecting, ordinary mercy offered to them: I ſay, God is not wont to Save ſuch a People by So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign Grace; he doth ſeldome (if ever) ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſede this courſe &amp; proceſs of his with ſuch a People by Sovereign Mercy; he doth rarely Save ſuch a Generation who have firſt provok<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him to enter into Judgment, by Sovereign Mercy. It is therefore dangerous to preſume upon Sovereign Grace.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>We muſt</hi> remember alſo, that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of Sovereign Mercy is made only to Mourners, to a People brought down to ſuch a depth &amp; degree of mourning &amp; humiliation, that their Spirits, their Hearts, their Souls, are ready to faint &amp; fail within them; ſo expreſly in the text of that promiſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.16.18—<hi>With him alſo who is of an humble &amp; contrite Spirit, to revive &amp;c. For I will not contend for ever— for the Spirit ſhould fail before, and the Soul which I have made. I have ſeen his ways &amp; I will heal him, I will reſtore comfort to him and to his mourners, &amp;c.</hi> Truly we muſt Expect that God will make <hi>New-England</hi> Mourn, until our Spirits, our Hearts be ready to faint within us; before he will Save us by Sovereign Grace: with theſe cautions all the ſincere People of God, in the Land, may &amp; ought to ſet themſelves to believe &amp; pray with confidence &amp; comfort for the accompliſhment
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:47161:31"/>of this glorious promiſe of Salvation: and have not good but great incouragement ſo to doe, for as much as,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Though our condition reſpecting our ſins and Gods wrath &amp; Judgment, for them, be very dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, yet it is not deſperate; there is always hope for the People of God: When there is not any, no not the leaſt or moſt remote appearance of hope, from man or means, either Ordinary or Extraordinary; Yea though there may be all the moſt prodigious ſigns &amp; formidable appearances, and inevitable ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches of deſtruction both by Sin and Judgment: Yet ſtill there is hope in God, and he would have his People to underſtand it, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.27. <hi>Why ſayest thou O Jacob and ſpeakeſt O Iſrael, my way is hid from the Lord, and my Judgment paſsed over from my God, haſt thou not known, hast thou not heard, that God, the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting God the Lord, fainteth not nor his weary &amp;c.</hi> Yea God incourageth his People to hope in their moſt deſperate caſes, <hi>Jer</hi> 31.16, 17. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frain thy voice from Weeping and thine eyes from tears, for there is hope in thine end:</hi> Jer. 29.11. <hi>I know the thoughts that I think towards thee, thoughts of peace &amp; not of evil to give you an expected end.</hi> God ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times gives his People, <hi>The Valley of Achor for a door of hope, Hoſ.</hi> 2.15 Opens to them a door of hope in the greateſt depth of diſtreſs: There is always <hi>Hope in Iſrael,</hi> in the moſt deſperate caſe, <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.2. <hi>Yet NOW there is hope in Iſrael concerning this thing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. That we have not only hope, but <hi>a ſure Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Faith &amp; Confidence in God for Salvation</hi> (viz.) <hi>His Covenant and all his promiſes,</hi> whereby we are aſſured, that he is not only able, but graciouſly Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:47161:32"/>to Save us: reſerving to himſelf the abſolute liberty of his Sovereignty, either to Save or Deſtroy, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.16. <hi>O houſe of Iſrael cannot I do with you as the Potter.</hi> But God hath not yet taken away his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant from us, he hath not yet ſaid of us (as of this People in our text) either <hi>Loruhamah, I will no more have mercy,</hi> or <hi>Loammi, ye are not my People, I will not be your God;</hi> nor broken the ſtaff of <hi>Beauty</hi> or of <hi>Bands.</hi> He doth yet own us and call us his People, and give us leave to call him our God, yea our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>and our Fathers God</hi> alſo. We may yet Pray in Faith as the Church, Iſa. 63.15. <hi>Look down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and behold, from the habitation of thy Holineſs, and thy glory, where is thy strength, thy zeal, the ſounding of thy bowels, and thy mercy, are thy reſtrained?— Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs thou art our Father:</hi> and as Iſa. 64.8, 9. <hi>O Lord thou art our Father—behold ſee we beſeech thee, we are all thy People:</hi> and as Jer. 14.9. <hi>Yet thou O Lord art in the midſt of us we are called by thy Name, leave us not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>God delights to Save his People by Himſelf,</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by moſt gloriouſly to magnify his own Wiſdom and Power above man and means; as in our <hi>Text: I will Save them by the Lord their God, and will not Save them by Bow, nor by Sword, nor by Battle, nor by Horſes, nor by Horſemen:</hi> Obſerve, God would not Save them by Ordinary means, but by Himſelf, that he might exalt himſelf in his own Strength, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 21.13. <hi>Be thou exalted in thine own Strength, ſo we will ſing and praiſe thy Power.</hi> Sometimes God Saves his People by terrible things in Providence, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 65.5. <hi>By terrible things in Righteouſneſs wilt thou anſwer us, O God of our Salvation.</hi> By wonderful viſiciſſitudes of Providential diſpenſations, the Wheels of Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:47161:32"/>are ſometimes ſo <hi>high,</hi> that they are <hi>dreadful, Ezek.</hi> 1.18. This made the Apoſtle to break forth, into higheſt expreſſions of Admiration and Adorati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with doxology, Rom. 11.33. <hi>O the depth of the riches, both of the wiſdom and knowledge of God; how unſearchable are his Judgments, and his Ways paſt find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out; who hath known the mind of the Lord? Or, who hath been his Counſellor: For of him, and through him, and to him are all things, to whom be glory for ever, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</hi> There will be a time, when the Church ſhall ſing the Song of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the <hi>Lamb,</hi> Rev. 15.3. <hi>Gaeat and marvellous are thy works, O Lord God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty, juſt and true are thy ways, O thou King of Saints.</hi> O that <hi>New-England</hi> may live to have her part in this Song.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If God ſhall thus Save us by himſelf: <hi>It will be the most full, perfect, ſaving and glorious Salvation that over God worketh for his People in this World.</hi> He will magnifie <hi>New-England</hi> again before the World; he will make us again a Praiſe in the earth, by cauſing our righteouſneſs to go forth as brightneſs, and our Salvation as a Lamp which burneth, Iſa. 62.1, 7. God will glorifie himſelf before all people in us, when he ſhall thus Save us from our ſins &amp; apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, by the power of his Spirit, in a general work of Converſion and Reformation; and by a glorious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Religion, in the life and power of it; and by the return of his ſpiritual and gracious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence unto us in the fulneſs of it; and ſo by cauſing his face to ſhine <hi>upon us.</hi> O this will be glorious Salvation! and that is the Salvation which I have in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended and ſpoken of all along; and when this Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation comes, then ſhall that great Promiſe unto the Church be fulfilled to us, Jer. 33.9. <hi>And I will
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:47161:33"/>cleanſe them from all their</hi> Iniquity, <hi>whereby they have ſinned againſt me; and</hi> I will <hi>pardon their iniquities,— and it ſhall be unto me for a Name of joy, a praiſe and an honour before all Nations of the earth, which ſhall hear of the good that</hi> I <hi>will do to them, and they ſhall fear and tremble, for all the goodneſs, and for all the Proſperity that</hi> I <hi>ſhall procure unto it.</hi> In that day will God accompliſh that great Promiſe unto us, Zeph. 3.17. In <hi>that day it ſhall be ſaid unto Jeruſalem, fear not,— the Lord thy God is in the midst of thee, mighty, he will ſave, he will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joice over thee with joy, rest in his love to thee, joy over thee with ſinging.</hi> O bleſſed, will ſuch of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God be, who ſhall ſurvive, or hereafter live to ſee the accompliſhment. Yea, bleſſed ſhall we be, may we dy in the Faith, hope, confidence and comfort of the accompliſhment of this Promiſe, in Gods time to his people and Churches here: <hi>I will have mercy upon</hi> New-England, <hi>and I will Save them, by the Lord their God.</hi> What remains then but that we believe, pray and wait for as much as <hi>the Lord waiteth that he may be gracious to us, and he will be exalted that be may have mercy upon us, for the Lord is a God of Judgment, and bleſsed are all thoſe that wait for Him.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:47161:33"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
